Finding Aid for Kenneth A. Easlick papers, 1924-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kenneth A. Easlick papers 1924-1979
Easlick, Kenneth A. (Kenneth Alexander), 1893-1979.
3 linear feet.
851158 Aa 2
Professor of dentistry at University of Michigan; personal materials relating to World War I service, speeches, correspondence, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 3756 ) was the gift of Dr. Easlick and came to the library in several accessions beginning in 1961.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Kenneth A. Easlick was born September 12, 1893 in Ridgeway, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1917, then volunteered for service with the U.S. Army Ambulance Service and was assigned to detached service with the French Army. He served two years, then spent about five years working with the Reynolds Spring Company of Jackson. He returned to the University of Michigan and received his dental degree in 1928. That same year, he was appointed clinical instructor in operative density.
Easlick became director of the Children's Clinic at the University of Michigan in 1930. He also became a member of the American Society of Dentistry for Children in 1932, only five years after its formation, and served on its college curriculum committee from 1936 to 1946, when the organization was fighting to see that pedodontics (dentistry for children) was included in the courses given to dental students.
Easlick served on the editorial board of the ASDC "Journal of Dentistry for Children" for six years, and was a member of its executive council from 1939 to 1942. He was a member of the American Board of Pedodontics from 1942 to 1961 and was made a diplomate of that board in 1948. He moved through the academic ranks to professor of dentistry and public health dentistry in 1945, and held that position until 1964, when he became professor emeritus of dentistry and public health dentistry at the University of Michigan. He retired from the University in 1963, after serving 35 years on the faculty. He died on December 21, 1979 at the age of 86.
The Easlick collection consists of materials relating to his service in World War I with the U.S. Army Ambulance Service Section 591, including copies of Le Jubicourt Matin, a journal of the reminiscences of the men of Unit #591, bulletins, a photograph album and miscellaneous correspondence and directories. Other materials in the collection include speeches, correspondence, and miscellanea relating to his career in children's dentistry. The collection concludes with a presentation volume of remembrances received upon his retirement in 1961, a volume of remembrances received from his students in 1964, and letters of condolence.
Subjects:
Dentistry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dentists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; United States. Army. Ambulance Service. Section 591.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Jubicourt matin.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Easlick, Kenneth A. (Kenneth Alexander), 1893-1979.; Finance.; Military art and science.; Military facilities.; United States. Army. Ambulance Service. Section 591.; World War, 1914-1918.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.
- United States Army Ambulance Corps, Unit #591
  - Le Jubicourt Matin (Box 1)
    (a semi-annual journal containing reminiscences of the men of #591)
    - 1922-1967 incomplete, 23 volumes (Box 1)
  - U.S.A.A.C. Bulletin, 1934-1977, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (scattered issues)
  - The history of the United States Ambulance Service with the French and Italian Armies, 1917-1918-1919 (1967) (Box 1)
  - Memoirs of 591 in the World War by DeWitt C. Miller, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Papers, ca. 1924-1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (includes correspondence, directories, etc.)
  - Easlick Genealogy, from 1810-1900 compliled by Kenneth A. Easlick (Box 1)
    (includes a portion of the chapter dealing with his service in World War I (incomplete))
- Speeches and related materials
  - 1932-1937, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - 1937-1941, 18 folders (Box 2)
  - South American dental publications, some featuring Kenneth Easlick, 1940s (Box 2)
- Correspondence, clippings, and other papers
  - 1941-1960 and 1974, 20 folders (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - World War I photograph album, 1917-1919 (Box 3)
  - Photos detached from album (Box 3)
- Personal; later career
  - Volume of letters received in 1961 upon occasion of his retirement (Box 3)
  - Volume of remembrances of Easlick by his former students, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Condolences and letters of remembrance received by his family in 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Letters received in 1973 after receiving award from the American Society of Dentistry for Children (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous awards and citations (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and clippings (Box 3)